I don't know how much Sean has told you about... Not very much.
You mentioned that you were...
He was surprised in some cases, but interested in my background.
And said, well, I know somebody who would like to talk to you.
And then...
You mentioned in your email what your phone is.
Yeah.
I'm just, I'd like to do background on people I'm interviewing.
So I did a little digging, and just to see that you worked here in the 90s, is that right?
Did you work here in the 90s?
Is that what the term is?
Yeah, I came 1985, and...
Retired the first one in 2000, then they called me back.
It's like bad cars, they get recalled.
So I retired again in 2002 and again in 2003.
You can't stay away.
Well, my replacement kept either quitting or not coming.
Yeah, I know.
So, and at that time, in fact, that's what I came for, is they had...
the beginning of a separate telecommunication program, separate from electronic, the common base for, I guess, a freshman and sophomore, and then they branch out into a telecom.
And my role was to develop the telecom part.
When they did call me back, I said, well, I'm retired.
They said, yeah.
Okay.
That's a tricky situation.
It's like they got you there.
They know which button to push.
Very much.
I wasn't forced to.
Right.
So I'm going to be honest.
I know
about technology, I'm not very technologically savvy, so I was doing a little background research too into your field, and it very quickly turned into another foreign language to me.
But it was so interesting seeing how you were part of the great technological shift on the university, like you were part of that, you were there, you saw that.
that period of time telecom was booming and the technology was also moving so very fast.
But we actually got after the third year a separate accreditation for the telecom program, EBIT accreditation, so that was good.
Yeah, absolutely.
We were, I think,
The second strictly telecom program, as opposed to electronic, electricity.
and the first undergraduate to get accredited.
So that was good.
Yeah, absolutely.
How was that, sorry that I'm jumping right into this, but how was that process of getting accredited?
Like, what did that entail?
Oh, that's the very long process.
It's a lot, you know, there's this much paperwork.
They want to know all the description of it,
program, how many people, students do you have, how many graduates, how many are employed, etc.
But each course, we get a detail, not just a summary, they want to see everything on the course.
It's a very long preparation process.
And, you know, everybody has to do it, but
Does that go to like, whenever you finish that, does that go to like a national type of?
Yes.
And so you submit that, and so professors of other universities that have a telecom program or something related or are professionally involved in telecom,
review all of these and then decided, yeah, let's go visit or not.
And so there's a group of three or four people that come and spend two or three days here looking at the labs, looking at the talking, interviewing the students.
It's a good process, but it takes a lot of time.
Yeah, I could definitely see that.
I would love to get you in touch with this gentleman named Mark Baggett.
He does the technological services for the library, but he has access to the supercomputers that we have here.
So I was like, I feel like that's something that... Well, that's a different orientation.
Yeah.
But can I rewind and go back a little bit?
Can you tell me about where you were born and where you were raised?
I was born in Paris, France, just before World War II, 1937.
And we had to, because of the German army invasion of France, we had to move
I think three or four times during that period to, well, it's, I was just a kid.
I was a little kid, so, but I do remember suddenly, no, we gotta go.
And it was not like,
Who was in your family at that time?
Well, it's, I was an only child, but my, let's see, yeah, my biological father had to leave because of the war situation.
But later on, I guess, I don't know the details, but my parents divorced.
And again, I know he had gone overseas.
And I don't know the details.
Mother didn't want to talk about it.
But she remarried.
And amazingly, that new father of mine, I mean, he literally adopted me.
And we went through the war.
And he took a chance.
He was, I don't remember which level, co-director of a factory.
And of course, German took that over and so we left again.
So it was, and all the bombardments and this and that.
Can I ask his name and your mom's name?
I don't know if they want that.
Oh, okay, that's fine.
Yeah, I think I'll answer that.
Yeah, absolutely.
Sorry.
No, no, no, that's fine.
Well, actually, my biological father, you can have his first name was Rene, R-E-E.
He had a, from what I read much later on, he had a PhD in marine biology.
Oh, how unique.
And in fact, went to, that was after the war was over, went to New Caledonia, which is a small island in the Pacific, north of New Zealand, way north of it, and set up an aquarium there.
They founded the aquarium and became quite famous in this field.
Wow.
He published three big books.
But I actually only left, that was a year and a half, I think.
And I never met him.
Well, that's on the other side of the world, literally.
Right, yeah.
But your mom, how strong, how strong?
Wow.
Yeah.
She had to face lots of other problems.
Well, the single mother and, you know, the financial input had disappeared, so she had to find a job.
And, yeah, and she has her own Ph.D., Ph.D. in sociology.
Wow.
So I had two...
imposing parents.
Yeah, very educated.
How did you end up in Texas, of all places?
That was a long circuitous study.
I studied in France for high school, of course, and then
junior college, but it was specialized.
It was strictly radio and electronics, except for some civics type.
And then I did my military service in France for three years in their equivalent of the signal corps.
So I was
Since I had done two years of radio school, it made sense for them to put me there.
And after that, I worked in Paris for a year and a half.
And then a friend of mine, who I met in France several times,
said, I had mentioned it.
He said, you know, you need to come and visit us.
And I said, well, yeah, but financialization plus.
He said, well, and then he actually got me a work permit for a year.
So I went there.
And the idea was, well, I'll work and I'll save as much money as possible.
And then I'd play tours.
But it's not the case anymore, but we're talking 1964, 65.
The telecom technology in the US was easily 10 years ahead of the French one.
The telephone network, there was no internet.
digital transmission at that time, but a telephone network in France.
It was not a priority, and the telecom was government-owned, most of Europe.
Oh, I did not know that.
Yeah, almost, yeah, actually all of Europe.
The Postal Service and the telecommunications were government-owned.
And the telephone network, I mean, you know, this is not, it's what, 10 years after the end of World War II, they had a lot of other problems, and their decision was, yeah, we have a telephone network, we'll modernize it later, we gotta use the money.
For other things, yeah.
I discovered that very quickly, that this is fascinating.
I'm a ham radio operator, so I met some American ham.
I was in New Hampshire for that work.
One of them, actually, well,
I told him that my work permit was only expired.
And he said, well, you know, well no.
He had a small repair and installation shop for mobile radios.
And he was specialized in equipping and maintaining radios for fire departments.
Most of them volunteer fire departments around the South New Hampshire.
And he said,
I had the technician who messed up seriously almost six months ago, and I desperately need somebody.
Would you be interested?
Yep.
Well, let's see what I can do.
I guess he convinced the immigration folks that I really need somebody, and I haven't been able to find a small town in New Hampshire.
And so I got another work permit.
That worked out perfectly.
And while I was doing that, I met a young lady who is now my wife, and we've been married for 57 years, I think.
Wow.
So made the right decision, obviously.
So I worked there, and then same thing, you know, one year.
So I went to immigration in Boston and said, is there any way I can renew this?
And I said, no, surely by now I would have been able to find somebody.
Yeah, okay.
And we discussed, and I started the paperwork, and she, I still remember Lizzie went to talk to her boss, I guess, and came back and said, there is one possible, if you can find a teaching job, you can stay, we'll give you a, whatever it's called, it's not the green card, it's
Definitely a work permit and also a temporary status, I guess.
But you can't leave New Hampshire.
I said, okay, I can leave that.
But that was kind of mid-July.
I was like, ooh, school starts in, what, four weeks?
Yeah.
And that was marvelous.
That was the little town in Peterborough, New Hampshire.
Four different families went all around looking for, you know, do you need me?
And I had essentially given up.
I started making reservations to go back.
And I got one of my friend who was the retired Air Force officer, Colonel.
called me and said, I got somebody, but you gotta help.
I said, okay.
Turns out it's a junior college, and their math professor, a lady, turned really sick.
And I said, well, we need somebody to teach you to.
calculus one and two right okay uh i haven't done that but i did study that way back and so
He was the president of the college.
He wrote a letter and said, take that to immigration.
And the same lady said, well, OK, I'm impressed.
So now I had
And that was valid for two years, I think, yeah.
And so, and as I said, I had met my wife there, which, so I have now all kinds of reasons for being nice.
I asked her, it turned out she's from Germany.
which is interesting.
She's much younger than I am.
So we were the start of Europe.
When we decided we got serious with each other, we went to Europe to meet our respective in-laws.
My mother had lots of friends, a lot of friends.
She was working as a translator for German and English to French.
And I knew several of her friends were Jewish and had serious problems during the war.
And here I come with a German girl.
And I thought, well, wait, she's much younger than I am.
That certainly wasn't her fault, but even she was born after the war was over.
So I had all kinds of reasons prepared, but I had forgotten how to
French, especially the Parisians, think.
And they didn't say, but she's German.
They said, wait, she isn't French.
I wasn't prepared for that.
Yeah, well, I didn't go to the U.S. to specifically look for a French girl.
That was funny.
But we got along with our respective in-laws.
So after the two years in the junior college, I decided to go back to school.
So I got a student visa, University of New Hampshire, electrical engineering, and I got bachelor's and master's from there.
And in the process,
somebody say, you know, you're legal with your student status, but you've been here for so long, why don't you try applying for a green card?
And so I did.
And it's when I was a senior at the university,
I got a letter saying, you got the, okay, we've got the green carpet, you gotta go register for the draft.
Oh, the middle of the Vietnam War, right?
So I went there.
And I still remember the master sergeant who was interviewing me.
He said, yeah, OK, so what's your background, et cetera, et cetera.
I said, you know, I just did three years of military.
He said, wrong army buddy.
Yeah.
So sign up here.
And then toward the end, because then I had to take a physical and this, and then I came back to him and he said, you forgot to write your birth date.
Yeah, sorry.
He said, wait, you're over 27.
uh so you're right we need you to register but unless we declare officially a war you know you're too old yeah okay i guess that's accomplished so and uh so i about well several months later i got the green card and oh dang
You get to serve in one army and then almost.
Yeah.
And I wasn't, I had to think about that.
You don't really want to go to Vietnam and fight over there.
Well, yeah, I think it's worth it.
Besides, my wife had no interest in going back to live in Germany.
So she stayed here.
I think I'm staying here.
Yeah.
It's impossible.
What was, did your wife work?
Yeah, she, well, yeah, when I met her, she was working in the pharmacy, not as a pharmacist, but to help the customers and things.
And then when I decided to go to university, she, for some reason, followed me.
And she worked in the pharmacy there, but she was working part-time and going to secretary school.
Wow, okay.
So she was also really busy.
She had a green card already.
Oh, okay.
She came as, you know what au pair?
She was for an American, it was a major, I think.
for whom he babysitted his kids while he was stationed in Germany and done other things.
And so they knew each other very well.
And he said, come on over.
And then she was au pair with them for, I don't know, three years or something like that.
Pretty good amount of time.
Yeah.
so university uh yeah bachelor's master's and then i worked for what was named general telephone which is now uh verizon in in massachusetts just outside of boston
I was with them for five, five years.
And then did something I wanted to do for decades.
I wanted to go overseas and help the people.
But I mean, I'm not, you know, I'm not a doctor and I'm not.
So, but if they need help with,
maybe I can do training and things like that.
And so I had applied to the UN as a specialized agency called the International Telecommunication Union.
And one branch of that is development for less developed countries.
So I applied, I had applied already coming out of the radio school and they said, well, we don't take people at the technician level.
So once I got the actual degree, I reapplied and they said, yeah, that's good.
But we prefer, since you're going in those countries,
you really needed another, I mean, a higher degree.
And it turned out they were absolutely right.
In most of these countries, people will not take, I don't want to call it orders, but directives from somebody who is not at a higher level than they are.
And they were absolutely right.
So, okay, I got my master's and I applied again.
And it's very good.
We'd like to have you, but since you're going to be the specialist over there, they call it an expert, which is unfortunate because then you go there and...
Well, you're expert in everything telecom.
Well, no, I never worked at those guys.
They say they were there.
Anyhow, so you have some experience in the military and some, but again, you need to have a lot of experience, otherwise they're not going to listen to you.
So five years, ooh.
So that's where I went to work for General Telephone.
So after, and while I was there, after the five years, I reapplied.
No, I actually didn't.
I got a letter from the ITU saying, we revised your, not revised, we reviewed your application, and we noticed you got five years now.
We'd like to have you, there are three possible positions for you, and one was Equatorial Guinea,
And, you know, as the name indicates, they're right on the equator, right in Africa.
And so we think temperature and humidity here is bad, but over there, and they don't have air conditioning.
People were telling me, you know, we changed shirts at least twice a day, if not three times.
And I didn't want to go there alone, right?
So by then we had, the twins were born, so no.
Okay, what's the other one?
Saudi Arabia, with my wife and two daughters?
No, sorry.
Well, we have one in Jamaica.
Ah, that sounds good.
So I took that job.
That was for two years.
They asked me to stay for an extra year.
Then as I was ready to come back to the U.S., my boss's boss in Geneva, where the special agency is, actually came and said, we started something in Haiti.
We need somebody who speaks French.
Well, I think I qualified with that.
But Hayden?
Yeah.
He said, hey, how about take your wife and kids and come for a while.
You help us write the proposal.
You know, they can go around.
Well, and that was during Baby Doc, the dictator there.
But Jamaica had its own problem.
The two major political parties, and they were literally fighting each other.
They left foreigners alone, which
there were a whole region of Kingston, the capital of Jamaica, where, you know, just don't go there.
So we get to Haiti, and I mean, wait, what's going on?
It's so calm here.
Of course, I found out later why.
He'd get out of, you know, maybe the full dictatorship, so you don't mess around.
But I remember walking with him one evening, and we kind of lost our way, and we were in the harbor area.
And I thought, oh, that's not a good idea.
And people came to ask us,
not for money or, you know, what the heck are you doing here, but are you lost?
Can we help you?
That's different.
So based on that, many other things.
The job was very interesting.
So after discussion with my wife and then three daughters, we went there for three years, which ended up being six.
So did a lot of training and organizations.
And then my next post was going to be, still with the UN, was going to be in Brazil.
And I told my then, he was my direct boss, and I was in Geneva because I was project manager.
And I said, I don't speak Portuguese.
I said, you're going to a research center.
They all speak English.
Good.
But wait a minute.
Can I have some details of the different research center?
Yeah, telecom research center.
They're pretty advanced.
They have PhDs.
What do you want me for?
I don't have a PhD.
And I said, look, we've got all kinds of people, researchers.
What we need is something to keep them together.
And we need a team leader.
You've been the project manager there for three years.
OK, if you say so.
So talk to my wife.
No.
By that time the twins were 17.
We are going back to the U.S. You can go where you want.
Okay, at least get overruled.
So we came back to the U.S. And well, it's time to look for a job.
And one of our
Specialized magazine, the IEEE, the Institute of Electronic and Electrical Engineering.
They have many magazines.
And I looked at the job openings, the opening in Texas here, and I was like, hmm, for telecom specifically.
That's unusual.
That sounds good.
So we came and visited.
I got interviewed and I liked them.
So I told them, I had to convince all my
And one argument I use is to say, look, this is a nine-month contract, so I've got three months of vacation.
Think of all the time we're going to spend together.
Forty years later, they still remind me.
So when are we spending all this time together?
I'd say, yeah, it's a nine-month contract, but you do have 12 months of work, right?
But I mean, I don't regret it at all.
Right.
Admittedly, if I had known ahead of time, I probably wouldn't have taken it.
But I'm glad I did.
Yeah, absolutely.
It's, I mean, that...
So, 19 years, 19 and a half years here.
Wow.
You've been everywhere, it seems.
The summers were, you know, taken, well, one thing, as I said, telecom, technology was increasing and improving very quickly.
So one part of my summer is to catch up with this, because I should teach them, and that takes a long time.
Then the books are, by definition, at least a year behind, usually two, because it takes a year to write it.
I put my own notes based on what I had learned in conferences and in specialized magazines and get copyrights and things like that.
that takes a long time.
Then you have to find a way to get scholarship for these people.
You can't do that during the year.
And then also equipment for the lab.
So the summers were pretty busy.
My wife would often say, no, wait a minute.
Industry, you had
weeks guaranteed, right?
And here you can't?
I said, well, no, I've got to do that.
I figured with all the summer months where I was either not paid at all or a half salary,
I essentially worked nine and a half months for free.
Not consecutively, but over the... Wow.
Which, again, I don't regret.
When I left, we had three labs, telecom labs, with equipment, a couple million dollars worth of equipment.
When I came, there was...
there.
That also takes time, by the way.
But, you know, I had several offers from industry as I went along, and so obviously I'd stayed, and I guess I thoroughly enjoyed the relationship with the students, and I felt, you know, former students, some of them still
email me or we meet somewhere and they're grateful and we thank you so much.
I thought you hated my test.
I did, but they were very useful.
There's something to be said about that.
I really don't regret it at all.
So that's good.
Absolutely.
So the process of, because you said you came and there wasn't like a full program, so you helped build the program, essentially.
Yeah, that was my role.
That was my,
I guess it was official title in the department, I don't know if it was true in the college, but I was telecommunication course leader because I was developing all those, which is fine.
And I started as an assistant prof, but of course then you got to do a lot of research and publishing.
And I was reminded of that by the, by the department head, right?
Several of them over the, and I said, we love you here and you're doing your job, but you've got to do research it.
That's not what I came for.
I came for teaching.
Research, I can get a lot better funding in industry.
And they said, yeah, but I can't keep you as assistant prof.
I said, well, any alternative?
And I reminded them, you know, this is an accredited program, and I think I had something to do with it.
He said, absolutely, but the rule is, which is true,
And he said, well, you can be a lecturer.
I was a lecturer in grad school.
How about senior lecturer?
Let me check.
And he came back from the dean and said, yeah.
Okay, you're on.
All right.
But you realize you can never get tenure.
I didn't come for that.
If I'm in the ministry, they can kick me off in two weeks, right?
Here, I've got at least at the end of the semester.
That's very true.
I didn't realize that you would still have to
do research?
Oh, yeah.
If you want tenure, there's no research and publishing.
You've got to publish books, or at least articles, and preferably books.
And I had started writing a book on testing telecommunication equipment because, well, I've used those, I've seen those, but
So the students need it when they get that.
But that takes a lot of time.
And after the second chapter, I had already contacted the editor who was interested.
I said, you know, I know I told you I would do that, but it's either I continue with that at the expense of the students.
You can't do that.
So that was another reason why
And okay, from a, from a, what's the right word?
Sure, if you are an assistant associate prof, that sounds much better than senior lecturer, but who cares?
This is not what I came here for.
So you really enjoy the teaching aspect of it?
Oh yeah, totally.
Yes, very much so.
Again, you know, I had close up with the telecom.
Typically, I had in each course something like between 20 and 25 students.
So you can know that you can relate both ways.
And the, in fact, I told the seniors the first time, I said, okay, now that you're seniors, you can call me Pierre.
And they loved that.
One of my, yeah, I think his title was coordinated.
It's an assistant department.
Okay.
Who somehow one of the students mentioned that, you know, they go,
And he was a retired Air Force guy, recently retired.
And he said, that's not acceptable.
And he told the students, don't ever do that again.
Because students came and said, well, let me go talk.
And he gave me a hard time.
I said, you're going to lose respect for it.
The only reason they respect me is if I'm called by my last name, then I, you know.
They said, no, but it's just not done, which is true.
And then the department had overheard the discussion.
They said to him, he said, you're not in the military.
Yeah, you can relax it.
So that continued.
And the seniors loved it.
That was their graduation to senior level.
When I started, there was an introductory course to telecom for the sophomores.
And then a poorly defined telephone network, I think.
But as I said, that expanded a lot.
I had an industrial advisory board like most programs do.
but who were president or equivalent of telephone companies all over Texas and others.
You know, Southwestern Bell, NGTE.
And when I came at first, the first semester, it's a long, I don't know if I'm diverging too much.
these people involved with telephone companies, I'd ask, I guess the then College of Engineering, I'm trying to remember, well it won't be exact thing, but they said, look,
We need some telecom people.
Sure, you're sending us electrical or electronic people, but then we have to train them for six months because you don't teach this stuff.
the then dean of the College of Engineering, this is 1985, right?
Well, no, in fact, it was before I came, so now he said, oh, but what you want us to do, that's not university level.
That's, you know, that's a technician program.
He said, no, no, we want engineers, but we want a specialized engineer.
Sorry, we can't do that.
We don't do that here.
And so...
I don't remember the details since I wasn't there.
I'm just trying to recollect.
But somebody in the college said to them, said, wait, why don't you try the engineering technology department?
They are not training people for grad school.
They're training people for industry.
So they went.
And so in engineering technology, they said, yeah, we can do that.
So they started that one-and-a-half course I'm talking about.
And so when I came, those same people, presidents of different health workers, came, and we had a meeting.
I introduced myself and said, there are several ways I can orient that.
I did graduate from electronic programs.
Are you interested in them designing circuits or are you interested in them
applying the existing equipment and the best possible.
I'd say circuits we have from electrical engineers.
We got plenty of those.
That's not what we want.
We don't want to have spent six months training everybody.
Oh good, that's where I came from, system side.
And they were, so that I developed the different courses.
based on my experience but also saying okay but what do you people want more specifically what kind of technology are you using and so we started things to respond to that and because they were pleased with the department and with the graduates they started offering some equipment and that's and i remember
That was after several years.
But I kept a relationship with those guys, and we were fairly close.
And I asked one of them, I won't mention the company,
I said, you know, I'm impressed by the amount of equipment you're giving us and the scholarships.
He said, well, there's something special about your program.
We noticed your equipment within a semester or so has been set up and is working.
We know you're doing something with it.
There are other places where that thing just sits there for whatever reason for years.
So, yeah, I mean, and the scholarships too.
And because, well, okay, I get some credit there, because the program was good and correctly oriented, and because telecom was
All my students, if they had C or better, had a job before they graduated.
And some of them went on the internship.
But even besides that, they came here, and they would tell, which didn't please the recruiting folks over there.
They said, no, no, no, we want to talk to the engineering technology telecom group.
But we have many, yes, we know.
Yeah, they, I mean, everybody got a job.
You had to have a seat.
That's fair enough, right?
That's impressive.
One of the petroleum company, they had their own, like all of the large corporations, they have their own telecom network.
So they have a telecom group that takes care of that.
And they're the director of that group.
Now you ask them, you know, I would go and visit them.
That particular thing was in Chicago.
And I asked him over dinner, he said, you know, I'm really grateful that you are hiring my C students.
And they said,
Well, but I've told our recruiting folks, if they come from your program, add a letter to that, then you go up.
So your C's are my B's, and that's fine.
That's high praise.
I like that.
Yeah.
Yeah, it was great.
Well, you know, there's a big satellite antenna next to Thompson that was given to us.
And we used that until I left, I guess.
I hesitate to open the door and see what's inside because I know it hasn't been used since.
Yeah, I mean, it was great.
How did you keep up with, since the technology was changing so quickly, how did you keep up with that?
That was strenuous, I would say.
One thing is conferences.
I would go in the summer and sometimes during the year as well.
Big telecoms, some of them at the national level, conferences and people present their new stuff and they say,
people that can help you.
Yeah, you know, if you have any question of that, just give me a call or do it.
There are a lot of that I didn't know.
Right.
I had to learn.
So that was one main thing.
The other thing is I was, I had the possibility that I could go there and just
spend the day in the company looking around, talking to their engineers and things like that.
That helps a lot.
And they would say, you know, there is this thing, again, that was not internet yet.
We hadn't just emailed.
So, and specialized magazines.
Okay, yeah.
But, yeah, it takes a lot of time.
And some of the stuff says, wait a minute, I better go ask somebody here.
How does that work?
But I'm, you know, I was thoroughly interested in that.
So that, you know, you
you're willing to go deeper and longer than you would otherwise.
I remember talking with one of my colleagues from the English department, and I said, you guys are lucky.
things don't change much, right?
And so you got three months off in the summer.
He said, yeah, but you know how boring it is to teach Shakespeare's to freshmen again and again, and they couldn't care less.
Which is a good point, because since, except the first four years, all the courses I was teaching were at the junior and senior level.
And if they've reached that point, obviously, they're interested.
And that makes it, we had some very interesting discussion.
I used, not every year, but for quite a while.
I had once a week, I had an evening thing.
You guys come and ask questions.
And we bring pizza and just discuss whatever they're interested in.
So I was never bored.
Never bored.
You seem like the type of professor that students would seek out, that they would actually go to, feel comfortable with.
Well, and open office doors.
If I'm there, the door is open, unless there's a student that comes in and has some problem.
He or she doesn't want to, you know, other people are here.
But that helped, too.
And there were many national level conferences, but one in particular
was specifically for the telecom, I think, for the large companies that had their own private telecom.
So there's a whole group of people that you don't, well, the general public doesn't think of.
That's a telephone company or the internet company.
But they have very elaborate networks and they usually,
move with the technology faster than the telephone companies do because of budget and other reasons.
So I almost always went to these groups.
And after a while, in fact, when we became accredited, I got invited
and said, you can bring four of your students.
And so I would pick my four top students, and I told them ahead of time, you know, I'm not going to, this is not a condition, but if I take just my four students in, they can come with me, so they have to pay for the airplane thing,
The conference is free, the room is free, the food is free.
Oh, how fun.
And you're going to be in an environment where you have the most recent equipment.
Yeah.
That helped, too.
And, of course, I would meet these other telecom managers and, oh, we didn't know you had the telecom program.
Yeah, well, yeah.
Yeah, I always, it was good.
When the department offered me a nice retirement reception in the former student and
So the speech and thing, and in mind, I used the occasion to publicly apologize to my daughters and wife for never being there.
Well, never, but that's true.
Yeah, there was, I retired two more times, and then they said, well, we're not offering you that.
No, that was,
So good, so well done, that was worth three.
This seems silly that I haven't asked this yet, but how did you first get interested in telecom?
Ham radio.
That was definitely...
Yes, that was the start.
I started going to meetings, ham radio meetings, and then met others, and then got my...
In France, you had to build your own transmitter, too.
But, so, that was... And I had a mentor, if you want, ham...
And then that's why I went to that radio school after high school rather than wherever.
How interesting that something, I'm not saying it's simple, but something as simple as a hand radio got you
all the way from your country, all the way over here, and all these opportunities.
It's so interesting.
Well, and that first work permit was the AM radio guide.
And the, it changed my life, really, for something very good.
And,
you come to a brand new place, right?
Then you know nobody.
Just pick up your radio and talk through the repeaters.
Oh, you know, come to our meetings.
And so suddenly you've got four or five, six people that are their common interest and they know this and that.
So, yeah, that helped me considerably.
That's awesome.
That's so interesting.
And it's even in the military service that I was, well, I first went to MCO school and became a sergeant.
But that was...
in the single core, so in radio.
And then I was based not far from Paris because I graduated, it was the second day
or third in line when I graduated from NCO school.
So they, you had choices, right?
The first thing, the first guy, okay, what's your preference for the first year?
After that, we'll send you when we need it.
And I was like third, or something like that.
Definitely among the first 10.
And the guy said, well, sorry, all the places in Germany, because at that time, there was the British, the Americans, the French, but no more space there.
And there's also, oh, there's a place outside of Paris, that's our telecom training center.
That sounds good.
And I didn't tell him that, especially my parents live just across.
So they're half an hour on bicycle.
Oh, yeah.
That's perfect.
I was lucky there.
And in fact,
In that time, military service was mandatory in France.
So you had to go.
But they would take you wherever they needed, so you could find yourself, regardless of your background, as a truck driver or whatever.
But one of the hams in a monthly meeting was a
At that time, he was either major or lieutenant colonel, but he was, we saw him often.
He came, I guess he was stationed not far from Paris either.
And he told me and a friend who was also in the radio school, said, you know, if you want to be in the Civil Corps, the only way that you can be sure of that
is to enlist rather than wait to be constricted.
Constricted, yeah.
So mandatory worth 18 months, year and a half.
If you're enlist, that's minimum three years.
But so he said, your choice.
But I would recommend you do it that way.
And you also, you know, through your first year, you become a sergeant, which has some advantages.
And so I talked it over with my friend and said, yep, let's go that way.
And I remember my dad say, my adopted dad said,
You're going to get this.
Yeah, but oh, okay.
So that was a ham too.
In fact, the third year, the last year of the service, I was in that training center doing training for people to maintain and repair high power transmitters and things like that.
And we have a new commanding officer coming in.
And so, you know, we all wait for him, and he's in speech.
And I look at him.
He's in full uniform, of course.
I thought, I know this guy.
I couldn't figure out why.
and that was the guy and he said he called me in his office later we know each other and we're both hands but you do remember that um so um and it's not a personal thing but you know other officers are there so please remember
but as a reward there is a ham radio station on the floor above my office which has been inactive so you need to get that thing back on the air and use it to call and let people know that this is
That sounds like a good deal.
Yeah, I mean, all my life.
The decision to enlist, that must have been scary, especially considering the time period.
Yeah.
Yeah, I mean, there is a, especially now, I mean, I'm 88, so, but when I was still in New Hampshire, I remember a reunion on D-Day, June 4th, I'm sorry, June 6th, 1944.
And there were several retired officers there, including the one that got me that teaching job.
And so, well, where were you on your barbecue and things?
He says, where were you on D-Day?
I'm in the U.S. somewhere in the Pacific.
And I said, it comes to me, and I'm at least 10 years younger, if not 15, than they are.
Well, I guess I was the only one in Norfolk.
And I remember he said, you're enlisted at age eight?
You didn't ask.
I wasn't on the beach, but you asked him, where were you in Norfolk?
I was in Norfolk.
I happened to be a seven-year-old kid when you guys came along, and I was glad to see you.
But that was, yeah, I mean, during the war,
there were some very close calls.
In fact, we moved from Paris to the south of France because, I don't know if you know that, but the armistice with the German, the Germans said, okay, we're occupying the northern part of France and the rest is yours.
I mean, yours.
I mean, they're both France, but that's under
French authority, and this is, of course, that didn't last very long.
So we moved from Paris to the south of France.
And then when the Nazis occupied the south part, we moved out and went.
And I kidded my dad for a long time that we went to Normandy, not on the beach, right, on this small village.
And I kidded him afterwards, said, of all the places.
And he said, everybody knew that the Allied weren't silly enough to try to scale the Atlantic Wall with all the protection and all the forts and all that.
They're going to come from England.
Well, they came from England directly or from the Mediterranean.
And he's right at that time, including Hitler, unfortunately, he thought theater.
So it was quiet until about a year before 1944, because then we saw that we were in a small village.
There was a train line going through the village.
train with ammunitions and you name it, going back and forth.
So that was dangerous by itself, but the British Air Force and the American would
So there were two big hills in the village.
and they had caves to make Galvados the equivalent of Cognac, if you want.
So pretty deep.
So whenever there was an alert or you heard the bombers coming to half of the village go there, and sometimes they, certainly overnight and sometimes days and days.
And some of the bombs came,
pretty close.
I mean, we lucked out.
It's, yeah.
And then, you know, the German occupation of the village, and so, you know, they get all the food and, I mean, all the meat and all the goods
And you never knew what would happen.
Yeah, I mean, those two years were painful, to say the least.
And we looked out.
It could have been much worse.
I'm glad it turned out for the better.
Yeah.
And the village fortunately didn't have any strategic value, but so our village didn't get liberated by the Americans until August something, early August.
So, you know, the G-Day was June 6th, right?
Yeah.
two months, two and a half months before they got.
And meanwhile, they were fighting everywhere and the Germans were still there.
Sorry, I didn't mean to bring up anything painful.
Well, yeah, and then it was, it took me years before I could eat, you know, turnips and whatever, yes, and even carrots, because you eat those every day.
because the German officers said, you know, the butter, the meat, and what they didn't go to, you know, the NCOs, but not to us.
Plus, you never know, I mean, there were all the concentration camp business, and you never know
for you know in a in a way i was lucky because i was only five six seven years old and i didn't realize at that time how you know horrific yeah and i that's one of my regrets i never realized until much much later how much uh my dad
Having accepted my mother and me through all the stuff that he had to get through, we owe him a lot.
I think it's very brave of you.
to you've gone through all of that and then just to enlist i think it's very so sorry that's a personal comment but i think somebody who's gone through something like that and then still faces it head on that's very brave yeah there to get back to the food problem no i'm sorry um it was i was so thin that the war after you know the
liberation, the Red Cross sent me to Switzerland to go eat, really, for, I don't remember, several, maybe a couple of months.
I was a farmer that accepted, you know,
something to do that.
But yeah, I always know.
And yet, look, I'm 88, so I guess constitution, physical, was pretty good after all.
Yeah, you made it.
Yeah, it's, yeah.
What were some differences coming over to America, like even culturally?
Yeah, that was a big change.
But there's several things that just totally amazed me.
And I mentioned four, five, six families
but that was it.
The Air Force colonel and his family, they kind of adopted me, but the others, and yet they all spent a lot of time trying to find me a teaching job.
Wow.
That really amazed me.
In general, the reception
from, again, Peterborough is a small town, and that maybe that helps.
But I was, those people are really nice.
And, you know, inviting me for barbecues, for this, for family of occasions.
Of course, the
Yeah, we... And the guy that was in another, that offered me the second job, that was in another town.
But I don't think that would have happened in France.
Ham radio group, yes, but outside of that, these were not hams.
My boss was.
And another thing that I wasn't paid very much, understandably, but enough to buy a second-hand car.
It was old, but it was working.
Whoa, that's great.
People don't believe me when I tell them, but the gasoline was 25 cents a gallon in 1964.
So, of course, we were...
So I was able to go around.
Yeah, my...
My work permit didn't allow me to leave New Hampshire, but New Hampshire was pretty good and pretty good.
And the people were very friendly.
Another thing later on, when I started working for General Telephone, we bought a house, not right away, but, and
So I was an engineer, master's degree.
And the guy next to me was a truck driver.
And I thought, that's amazing.
It could never happen in France.
A, because, I mean, there's a social structure.
You couldn't be just a truck driver.
And the guy was very nice, by the way.
But I thought, that's fantastic.
It is a...
On the other hand, so it's not the social status, it's the salary that we were paid.
Yeah, obviously made good salary.
So people combine based on their financial status rather than social status.
But I kind of like that.
Now that you point that out, I guess that has a lot to do with the government.
Maybe?
Maybe the government?
Well, the history, I think.
I mean, France, Paris was, when I was there, 2,000 years old, and now it's another 200 years.
There's a whole, yeah, there's a, most of,
Western Europe, you know, England included, you know, there's a social thing.
Which is another thing that ham radio helped, because during those meetings there was no, you didn't talk about, you know, I'm, you know, Dr. So-and-so, you know, which was ham radio.
So that was true in France, too.
No, there were a lot of, and the opportunities later on, it, yeah, in fact, of course now it wouldn't work either, but I was going to say, in France, without a PhD, you can't be teaching at the university, period.
Here, that's true now, but because engineering technology was not preparing people for grad school, they say, okay, you don't have a PhD, but you've got 10 years of industrial experience.
So for us, that's actually good.
They no longer do that.
In fact, when I, one year I made,
the outstanding prof for, you know, the College of Engineering.
Each college has one, and I did it for the College of Engineering.
So big receptions and speeches.
And I was, so the ten of us are sitting together on the podium.
And I hear the lady at that time who was in charge of the faculty, she was reading some letters from my students and compliments and very nice.
But I was, so that's 19, I'm sorry, 2000, yeah.
But
If I applied now, you wouldn't even look at my horizon, because I don't have a doctorate.
So it's kind of ironic, but in France, there is no exception.
You can't teach at a university, you don't have a PhD.
Interesting.
So that was a plus.
And even, well, the junior college, they wouldn't require, but a technical school in France, no, there you don't need a PhD either.
So there's definitely more opportunities here than to think.
Things have changed in Europe a lot, but in that time, it was much more structured.
Yeah, that makes sense.
This life here is very comfortable.
Lots of, what's the right word?
Lots of stuff you couldn't do elsewhere, I think.
It's a bit frenetic.
There is something in France and the other Western European countries
You have five weeks of vacation.
Paid.
So you've got a lot more time to spend with your kids.
That I missed.
And you could travel.
I mean, I used to travel with my parents until I was 21 or something like that.
We would still go together because
There's no perfect place, but I'm certainly grateful to this one, which is why I joined the Coast Guard Auxiliary, which is the volunteer branch of the Coast Guard, and I just completed my 25th year with that.
That was my way of saying thanks.
here, maybe I can help.
Yeah, still, wow.
Yeah, I got my fourth golden star.
The ribbon is the first five years, and each gold star is another five years.
Yeah, that, in fact, I, yeah.
So I still do that.
Of course, I don't go on patrols anymore, boat patrols anymore, and
stuff because I don't have a strain and I have usual age problems.
But I'm still a member, I'm still their communication officer for some strange reasons.
I was the HR officer for the division level for, I've retired, I stepped down from that last year because I was forgetting too many things.
It's embarrassing when you're HR, you deal with all the newcomers, right?
Then you help, you have to do this and this.
And then three weeks later, the guy would come back and
So, but I mean, that's normal.
But yeah, in fact, we are, we're going to have, our, we call that the flotilla, that's more good, is on Lake Conroe.
And we're going to have a common maneuver training the end of May, May 30th, together with a regular coast guard.
They have several rescue and fireboats and the lake constable.
We do a common maneuver, which is part of training.
We do search and rescue type thing.
Normally it's done on Galveston Bay.
And we, yeah, we're the volunteer branch.
We don't do law enforcement, but everything else.
Public education, boat inspection, we do public affairs, radio communications when needed.
And essentially whatever the regular Coast Guard
to do.
It goes all the way to cooks, I mean chefs that were chefs in their previous life and are retired.
And in fact that started in our division when the
I don't think it was the captain, but one of the officers of the regular boat crew said, wait a minute, you have people who know how to cook?
Yeah, we need them.
We don't have enough.
We have boats that cannot go out on shore because the only thing we have are sandwiches.
And so there we have people that go help them out Galveston.
but also fewer of them because you now have to go spend a week or two offshore with that.
But yeah, and they, so we also have people who help them administratively speaking, because they, the regular culture is so busy these days.
um well both from a uh protection of the coast that's a joke right but blocking uh and and you name it and that's the role that they used to have which included
boating safety of the public, right?
They say, look, we really have less and less time.
You guys do that.
So that's why we do patrol in Galveston Bay regularly and we have that on Lake Conroe and many of the lakes to reduce the number of accidents and deaths on the water.
So since you've gone all over, moved everywhere, do you have anything else on your bucket list?
Any places you want to visit?
Well, I've been to quite a few places.
That's the thing.
You know, I mentioned the five-week vacation with my parents.
We could go all over Western Europe.
I did go to Eastern Europe to what was then Czechoslovakia as part of my job that first year for just a couple of weeks.
But Prague is a very nice city.
And my wife is actually from East Germany.
So we went together with her brother visiting, you know, where they were born.
And that was interesting.
In fact, the mayor somehow, I guess her brother just went to the city hall to say, we're here for a visit and we,
interested and rejoined us and took us around.
It was really nice.
Yeah, I've been to lots of places.
Also, I was a part-time contractor with
USAID, which doesn't exist anymore.
One department of USAID was the Office of Foreign Disaster Assistance.
They go and help people right after, you know, hurricanes, volcanic eruption, to help wherever needed.
And of course, one problem, especially the smaller Caribbean islands, is they get wiped out.
And they have no way to call for help.
Well, dependent situation.
So one of the things I did with another ham, who was working for them full-time, is we would go down and
do a temporary either shortwave radio communication or we had a portable satellite station and set it up so they can talk either to Geneva, the Red Cross, or to Washington for the
the health organization.
Doctors Without Borders?
No, no, I mean the government.
Well, it's international, not international, multinational, power, something.
It's at the tip of my tongue, too.
The H.O.
is Health Organization.
Oh, Pan American Health Organization.
For example, sometimes they would ask USAID, can you send us some guys?
So, went to Guatemala, do that.
Didn't do much others.
Well, Mexico, yeah, we did sailing to Mexico several times.
Atlantic side, and yeah, a lot of Western, essentially most of Western Europe.
I have lots of cousins, distant cousins.
We had one major family, greater family reunion in November of 2000, first year I was retired.
organized by people over there.
And we had about 110 or 114 people from nine different countries.
All descended from the same great-great-grandfather.
And we were in that, it took place in the town where those grandfathers had lived.
How incredible.
And, I mean, there was, we had people, yeah, including a family from Hungary.
And at that time, in 2000, there was free traveling again.
They had to go through all kinds of things.
They drove all the way down to the east of France to join us.
That's where my family's from, Hungary.
Yeah.
And so we have people from Italy.
Interestingly enough, nobody from Spain.
Catala is definitely, it's from the northern, northeastern part, the place called Catalonia, in fact, which is a province.
that in their language, Catalan, Catalan means somebody from Catalonia, so we know we have ancestors there, right?
But we couldn't go that way.
So it was strange that we had people from Argentina, we had people from India, lots from England, Germany, Italy, France, of course.
And I visited a lot of these people because
That group that organized this reunion, then two years later, well, we go to another country.
And by that time, I was part of the committee.
Yeah, traveling, I did a lot.
The evening to Canada, after I was here.
Well, one of our daughters lives in Washington State, almost in Canada, on the Pacific Ocean.
So we have a camper van and we, several times, three times, we've gone there and took our time going and spent a month there and then come back to different routes and, in fact, through Canada.
Wow.
Yeah.
World traveler.
Let's see.
Of course, Haiti, Jamaica.
And while I was there, so I was working for the International Telecommunication Union, but the United Nations,
I'm sorry.
No, no, it's fine.
Anyhow, they also, that's the specialized agency, the UN, that deals with disasters.
And when I was in Haiti, one of the, usually all the project managers would get together once every two months or so to exchange ideas.
And he said, oh, you're in telecom.
We need help in the Caribbean with that.
I said, okay.
I got a full-time job here.
I said, who's your boss?
Geneva.
I said, oh, I live in Geneva, too.
They organized something, and I was allowed to take, I don't remember, four days off a month to go.
I visited the different islands, all the independent ones, not Puerto Rico and the ones that are still territories.
need help.
So I would stay several days in this island and another month in that island, which, yeah, I know the Caribbean very well.
Wow, what a life.
You've lived so much and you've seen so much.
Yeah, I've been, ever since the war stopped, I've been very lucky.
Interesting.
I know you mentioned how you were writing some chapters to a book, but I think you should write your own book about places you've been to.
I'd read that.
I'd for sure read that.
Yeah.
I don't have any more questions.
Did you have anything that you wanted to talk about that I didn't get to?
Well...
Yeah, a couple of things.
One thing when I did decide to come here is when I thought, oh good, I'm gonna stop all the political problems that you work for the UN and in a foreign country,
you've got to deal with a lot of different things.
First, you've got colleagues that are from five different countries.
We all have our own views of things.
And those are the five experts.
And then you've got our counterparts.
And, of course,
the whole country, right?
And there are things that are perfectly okay in the U.S., but not at all okay.
And you don't have time to learn, you learn the hard way.
So, I mean, again, you know,
Not regretting any of that.
But it's different.
It's different.
Haiti in particular is a very poor country.
And they have a former French colony and the history of slavery.
and there are things that you just don't do.
So if you ask something from somebody in a way that can be answered by yes or no, they can't say no.
Oh, okay.
Can't say no to a superior, right?
And especially a foreigner.
A brown, yeah, white guy.
So they say, yes.
And then you said, you finished that.
I tested it.
It's not working.
I said, no, I don't know how to do that.
But I asked you if you'd done it.
Yes.
What's going on?
So I went to see my colleague, my counterpart, who's an engineer.
He said, well, no, it's not an acceptable answer.
So you've got to make sure you ask.
In fact, one time we were looking for a place for a microwave repeater.
We were in countryside, jeep, fording rivers.
And on the way back, I got totally lost.
There was a lady sitting in front of a hut, literally.
And I asked her, you know, is this the way to Port-au-Prince?
Guess what she answered?
Yes.
So I go there and we drive for hours, maybe not, but for a long time.
I said, I don't recognize anything like this.
Turn around.
It wasn't my counterpart, but one of the Asian colleagues, he was in training, he was an installer.
said, do you mind if I ask a question?
I said, please.
So he said it in Creole, not in French, but I understood.
He said, which is the way for Port-au-Prince?
And I said, that way.
And I thought.
And it happened.
Well, yeah, I should have.
Cultural differences.
Ideally, you have
in advance notice, you got a month to read about, but that's not the way things happen.
I had one week and a half to make a decision whether I would go to Haiti or not.
It's, yeah, that was interesting.
Cultural differences, yeah.
See, I wouldn't even think about that.
I would have that problem as well.
Yeah, it's their history, and they still suffer from it.
And actually, the other problem is even within a telephone company, the position that you occupy
really a political assignment.
So, at least at the higher level.
So you have a situation where a supervisor, and I pointed out, said, did you see what he did?
Yeah.
That's dangerous.
Yes, but I don't want to give him a hard time.
Because two months from now, maybe the doc might put him as my boss's boss.
So, can I tell him?
Yes, please do.
So even in those instances, you still have to play politics?
Yeah, well, so, yeah, you're right.
I diverged.
Oh, no, no, no.
So I thought, I'm through with all this political process.
No.
It follows you, yeah.
That was a surprise.
Although I've been very lucky with all my department heads.
Some interesting times.
Yeah.
Again, if I had known that I wouldn't have any vacation, I probably would have said not because I had an offer from industry in San Diego.
And of course, but that's the way it is.
I wouldn't have a chance to have this relationship with the students.
Yeah, true.
Thank you for meeting me and telling me your story, a bit of your story.
I'm glad if it could be useful.
Absolutely, it is.
Absolutely.
We have roughly 2,000 interviews from the 60s all the way up to the early 2000s.
One of them was the director of our library, Cushing, and the other one, Terry Anderson.
He's still here.
He's a history professor.
I don't know if you know him.
I know the school's huge, but he's still here.
And so once I got hired and I basically got all of his work that he had, I was like,
It's so nice to meet you, and I'm the one handling all of your interviews that you've given.
He's like, oh, no, those things, put them back in the closet.
Put them back in the closet.
Yeah.
Oh, good.
Thank you so much.
Very welcome.
Yeah.
Good to help.
Yes.
I will be in touch.
I will make sure you get copies of everything.
Now your wife sounds like someone I should talk to too.
She is quite a lady.
She skipped me for 57 years, that by itself.
She's the nurse, or was a nurse.